Guide to the Lloyd Appleton Metzler Papers, 1937-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lloyd Appleton Metzler papers 1937-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Metzler, Lloyd A. (Lloyd Appleton).
14.0 linear feet Extent: Approximately 10,300 Items
Economist, University of Chicago faculty member, and consultant to a number of U.S. government agencies. Collection spans the years 1937-1974 and consists chiefly of Metzler's correspondence, notes and drafts, printed material, course-related materials, and typed copies of works by Metzler and others. Significant correspondents include Paul Samuelson and Kenneth Arrow. Most items relate to his career as an economic consultant for several U.S. government agencies including the Federal Reserve Board (1940s). Others relate to his work as a professor of economics at the University of Chicago. Topics covered by his papers include post-World War II policy and planning, British-American economic negotiations after the war, German monetary reform, monetary aspects of international trade, exchange rates, income transfer, instability theories, and the application of mathematics to economic theory. Collection is minimally processed and may need further processing before materials can be used.
RL.00893
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lloyd Appleton Metzler Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Richard Appleton Metzler in October 1987.
Collection Overview
The Lloyd A. Metzler Papers span the years 1937-1974 and consist chiefly of professional correspondence, research notes ad drafts, printed material, teaching material, and typed drafts or reprints of works by Metzler and others. Significant correspondents include Moses Abramovitz, Kenneth Arrow, Harry Johnson, James Meade, and Paul Samuelson, with many letters, particularly between Meade, Metzler, and Johnson (1940s-1950s), containing in-depth exchanges about economics. There are a few exchanges with Gottfried Haberler on international trade. Several folders contain significant notes from Metzler's own student days at Harvard in the 1930s with Joseph Schumpeter, Wassily Leontief, and O. H. Taylor. Many items in the collection relate to Metzler's wartime service as an economic consultant for several U.S. government agencies including the Federal Reserve Board, as well as his post-war work with the Department of State and with the Secretary of the Treasury on monetary policy, among other issues. Other items relate to his work as a professor of economics at the University of Chicago, and offer insights into the views he held on economics in the context of the Chicago School. Topics represented by materials in the collection include post-World War II policy and planning, including British-American economic negotiations after the war and German monetary reform; monetary aspects of international trade; exchange rates; income transfer; instability theories; and the application of mathematics to economic theory. Some files of research notes and paper drafts contain unpublished work; one draft contains handwritten comments by Viner. Collection is minimally processed and needs further processing before materials can be used.
Biographical Note
Lloyd Appleton Metzler was born in Kansas in 1913. As an economist he became known for his research on international trade, tariffs, the business cycle, macro-monetary theory, mathematical economics, and instability. The "Metzler paradox" relating to tariff theory was named for him, and in mathematical economics the "Metzler matrix" also bears his name. Graduating from Harvard in 1942, he was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship. He served as a consultant to several U.S. Government commissions and the Federal Reserve Board during World War II, and was a member of the Yale faculty from 1946-1947. He subsequently spent most of his career at the University of Chicago, where he was a Keynesian economist rather than following the Chicago School of thought. In 1973 Harvard University Press published Metzler's Collected Papers, which were chiefly written between 1941 and 1951. After 1952 a brain tumor presented major health problems and affected his scholarly output. Metzler was honored as a Distinguished Fellow of the American Economic Association in 1968. He died in 1980.
Subject Headings
Abramovitz, Moses; Arrow, Kenneth Joseph, 1921-; Economics -- History -- 20th century; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Foreign exchange rates -- History; Government economists -- United States; Great Britain -- Economic conditions -- 1945-1964; Haberler, Gottfried, 1900-; Harvard University -- Dept. of Economics -- Faculty; International trade -- Economic aspects; Johnson, Harry G. (Harry Gordon), 1923-1977; Meade, J. E. (James Edward), 1907-1995; Metzler, Lloyd A. (Lloyd Appleton); Monetary policy -- Germany; Monetary policy -- United States; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-; Economic stabilization; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; United States. Federal Reserve Board; University of Chicago -- Faculty; University of Chicago. Dept. of Economics -- Faculty; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects
Contents of Collection
- Lloyd A. Metzler Papers, 1937-1974, (11 boxes)
  - Former inventory containing more details on contents (though box arrangement no longer exactly applicable) (Box 1)
  - Unpublished papers (other authors)
    - Cowles' papers for the Activity Analysis Conference (early versions) (Box 1)
    - Arrow's instability theorem (early version) (Box 1)
  - The Chile Project, University of Chicago, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Sketches for papers (Box 1)
  - Exclusively Federal Reserve print materials and papers (Box 2)
  - University of Chicago teaching material (Box 3)
    - International economics (courses and class notes), 1950s (Box 3)
    - Theses (Box 3)
    - Transparencies (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Robert Mundell paper (circa 1964) on stability with comments by Metzler revealing his own views of Hicks and Samuelson's contributions (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Correspondence (A-H), (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Kenneth Arrow (Box 4)
    - R. G. D. Allen (Box 4)
    - Letters to Congressmen (Box 4)
  - Post-War Britain material
    - Post War Recovery by G. E. Robert Meyer, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (I-W) (Box 5)
    - Treasury Department correspondence (Box 5)
    - Paul Samuelson correspondence; lengthy letter to Metzler on stability in relation to Samuelson and Hicks (Box 5)
  - Metzler's papers, drafts of work (Box 5)
  - Teaching material
    - International Economics exams and course information, 1951-1960 (Box 5)
  - Metzler reprints (Box 6)
    - Stability paper (Box 6)
    - Graham's Theory of International Values (Box 6)
    - Flexible exchange ratios and the theory of employment (Box 6)
    - Tariffs, movements of international demand, and domestic prices (Box 6)
  - Matrix theory notes (algebraic) (Box 6)
  - Drafts
    - The rate of interest on the marginal pursuit of capital (Box 6)
    - World prosperity and the British balance of payments (Box 6)
  - Harvard teaching materials, 1930s (Box 7)
    - Volume of class notes from Joseph Schumpeter, Wassily Leontief, and O. H. Taylor, 1937-1938 (Box 7)
    - Division of History, Government and Economics. Division Examinations for the Degree of A. B., 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Metzler reports and papers, 1944-1946
    - Post-War British debts (Box 7)
    - Inventory cycle notes (Box 7)
  - Foreign Trade Agreement Report by the Committee on Ways and Means, May 1945 (Box 7)
  - Drafts (Box 8)
    - Material for Metzler's collected papers (Box 8)
  - Seminar and lecture notes
    - University of Chicago (Box 8)
    - Toronto (Box 8)
    - Department of State, 1949 (Box 8)
  - Collected papers material (Metzler) (Box 9)
    - Harvard Economic Studies, Harvard University Press (Box 9)
  - Teaching materials
    - Harvard class readings, 1938-1939 (Box 9)
    - University of Chicago exams, reading lists, and course information, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Collected papers (Box 10)
  - Reports, 1945-1970s (Box 10)
  - Federal Reserve material: working papers for staff, brochures, bulletins, research memos, 1943-1951 (Box 10)
  - Teaching material (Box 11)
    - Course exams (Box 11)
    - Reading material (Box 11)
  - Department of State correspondence (includes Metzler's biographical information) (Box 11)